<article>
  <header>
    <h2>Research</h2>
  </header>

  <p>My research centers on the interplay of software and hardware in
  <strong>post-Moore systems</strong> &mdash; specialized systems comprising
  tightly integrated and co-designed hardware and software components.
  I am interested in the nascent challenges in designing, implementing, and
  maintaining post-Moore systems in different application domains;
  starting with data center network communication and machine learning systems.
  My research develops abstractions, tooling, and methodology for building
  efficient post-Moore systems and applications with manageable complexity and
  cost, through modular and re-usable components.</p>

  <p><strong>In my long-term research agenda, I envision a future where
  specialized, tightly integrated, and efficient post-Moore hardware-software
  systems can be rapidly and efficiently prototyped and evaluated.</strong></p>

  <p>My research is practical in nature, taking ideas all the way to full
  prototype implementations, building concrete solutions to problems in several
  domains, and resulting in top-tier operating systems (SOSP, OSDI, EuroSys),
  networking (SIGCOMM, NSDI), and architecture (ASPLOS) publications
  alongside substantial open source releases.</p>

  <p>As processor performance in the post-Moore era continues to stagnate,
  satisfying the growing demand for more compute going forward requires radical
  changes throughout the systems stack.
  A proven strategy for continuing to achieve the required order-of-magnitude
  improvements is to move from today's general purpose platforms to post-Moore
  systems designed and optimized for specific problem domains.
  Currently, designing, implementing, and maintaining these systems is a
  complex, laborious, and risky process, accessible to few and only practical
  for the most computing intensive applications.
  I believe this is not fundamental, and have started to explore these
  challenges in the context of data centers before generalizing to other areas
  in the future.</p>

  <p>I have structured my main research agenda into three complementary
  directions addressing different  post-Moore systems challenges:</p>

  <ol>
    <li>Designing post-Moore systems to explore the design space for two
      application domains.</li>
    <li>Streamlining the evaluation of post-Moore systems.</li>
    <li>Enabling portability and modularity in the post-Moore era.</li>
  </ol>


  <h3>Projects</h3>
  Our group website has an
  <a href="https://os.mpi-sws.org/projects.html">overview of our research
  projects</a>.


  <h3>Collaborators</h3>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="https://dse.in.tum.de/bhatotia/">
        Pramod Bhatotia</a> (TU Munich)</li>
    <li><a href="https://people.mpi-sws.org/~jcmace/">
        Jonathan Mace</a> (Microsoft Research)</li>
    <li><a href="https://www.comp.nus.edu.sg/~lijl/">
        Jialin Li</a> (National University of Singapore)</li>
    <li><a href="https://people.mpi-sws.org/~dg/">
        Deepak Garg</a> (MPI-SWS)</li>
    <li><a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~simon/">Simon Peter</a>
      (University of Washington)</li>
    <li><a href="https://homes.cs.washington.edu/~rajaths/">Rajath Shashidhara</a>
      (PhD student, University of Washington)</li>
    <li><a href="https://sg.linkedin.com/in/yihang-yang-a8a1b41a0">Yihan Yang</a>
      (PhD student, National University of Singapore)</li>
  </ul>

  <h3>Past Collaborators</h3>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/tim-stamler-96336392">Tim
        Stamler</a> (PhD student, UT Austin)</li>
    <li><a href="https://keonjang.github.io/">
        Keon Jang</a> (Rubrik)</li>
    <li><a href="https://ymsir.com/index.html">
        Ymir Vigfusson</a> (Emory University)</li>
    <li><a href="https://www.cs.washington.edu/people/faculty/tom">
        Tom Anderson</a> (University of Washington)</li>
    <li><a href="https://www.cs.washington.edu/people/faculty/arvind">
        Arvind Krishnamurthy</a> (University of Washington)</li>
    <li><a href="https://homes.cs.washington.edu/~naveenks/">Naveen Kr. Sharma</a>
      (University of Washington)</li>
    <li><a href="https://homes.cs.washington.edu/~xi/">Xi Wang</a> (University
      of Washington)</li>
    <li><a href="https://people.eecs.berkeley.edu/~mangpo/">Phitchaya Mangpo
      Phothilimthana</a> (Berkeley/University of Washington)</li>
  </ul>



</article>
